Tony Schwartz Collection
Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress
Tony Schwartz collection1912-2008 1950-2008
Schwartz, Tony
90.5 linear feet (230 boxes, approximately 76,345 items)
Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The Tony Schwartz Collection consists of multiple formats of material documenting Schwartz's work as a media consultant, audio documentarian, author, radio producer, media theorist, and educator.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bemporad, Jack.; Bleviss, Alan.; Bredesen, Phil, 1943-; Carey, John, 1946-; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Cherner, Joe.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Dainard, Michael, 1944-; Dukakis, Michael S. (Michael Stanley), 1933-; Foley, Thomas S.; Gravel, Mike, 1930-; Hardin, Louis.; Hoffman, David (David Michael), 1941-; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Jamieson, Kathleen Hall.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Landers, Bob (Radio announcer); McFeeley, Ken.; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-; McLuhan, Marshall, 1911-1980.; Mezvinsky, Edward M.; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Moyers, Bill D.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003.; Napolitan, Joseph, 1929-; Pell, Claiborne, 1918-2009.; Pertschuk, Michael, 1933-; Reid, Harry, 1939-; Reynolds, Patrick.; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1937-; Rudman, Warren B.; Schwartz, Anton, 1967-; Schwartz, Kayla.; Schwartz, Reenah.; Schwartz, Tony--Archives.; Schwartz, Tony--Correspondence.; Schwartz, Tony--Photographs.; Schwartz, Tony.; Schwartz, Tony. Media, the second God.; Schwartz, Tony. Responsive chord.; Seith, Alex.; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969.; Skelton, Isaac Newton.; Vrdolyak, Ed, 1937-; Weiss, Ann.; Young, Andrew, 1932-
Organizations
American Cancer Society.; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists.; American Heart Association.; American Lung Association.; Center for Media in the Public Interest, Inc.; City University of New York.; Doctors Ought to Care (Organization); Emerson College.; Folkways Records.; Foundation for a Smokefree America.; Harvard School of Public Health.; John Jay College of Criminal Justice.; Martin Himmel Health Foundation.; New Sounds, Inc.; Non-Smokers' Rights Association.; Patrolmen's Benevolent Association of the City of New York.; People for a Smoke-Free Indoors.; Tisch School of the Arts.; United States Information Agency.; Varied Directions, inc.; WNYC (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
Advertising agencies--New York (State)--New York.; Advertising, Political--United States.; Advertising, Public service--United States.; Advertising--Psychological aspects.; Agoraphobia.; Antismoking movement--United States.; Broadcast advertising--United States.; City sounds--New York (State)--New York.; Communication and technology.; Communication in marketing.; Communication--Social aspects.; Documentary radio programs--New York (State)--New York.; Folk music--New York (State)--New York.; Folk music.; Human sounds--New York (State)--New York.; Magnetic recorders and recording.; Marketing research--United States.; Mass media.; Media consultants--New York (State)--New York--Archives.; Media consultants--United States.; Media literacy.; Political campaigns--United States.; Political candidates--United States.; Political consultants--New York (State)--New York--Archives.; Political consultants--United States.; Public relations firms--New York (State)--New York.; Radio personalities--New York (State)--New York--Archives.; Radio producers and directors--New York (State)--New York--Archives.; Sound engineers--New York (State)--New York--Archives.; Sound recordings--Collectors and collecting.; Sound recordings.; Sound--Recording and reproducing--United States.; Sounds.; Tobacco use--Health aspects.; Voice actors and actresses--United States.
Places
Hell's Kitchen (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; West Side (New York, N.Y.)
Titles
Guerrilla media.; Media industry newsletter.
Form/Genre
Address books.; Appointment books.; Articles.; Audio equipment.; Awards.; Awards.; Camera-ready copy.; Clippings (information artifacts); Commercials.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Group portraits.; Handbills.; Interviews.; Memorabilia.; Negatives (photographic); Photographs.; Portraits.; Posters.; Promotional materials.; Publicity photographs.; Radio programs.; Scripts (documents); Snapshots.; Sound recordings.; Surveys (documents)
Administrative Information
Collection Acquisition
The bulk of the collection was purchased from Tony Schwartz in 2007; two additional installments were donated by Tony Schwartz's family in 2010.
Additions
No further additions to the collection are expected.
Access Restrictions
Textual and graphic materials in the Tony Schwartz Collection are open for research. Advance notice is required; contact a reference librarian in the Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress, Washington, DC, 20540-4690; (202) 707-7833.
The films, videocassettes, and many of the sound recordings that are included in the collection are not yet available to researchers. For information concerning availability, contact a reference librarian in the Recorded Sound Reference Center.
Digital Format
Some of the audiotapes in the collection are available in digital form in the Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress, Washington, DC, 20540-4690; (202) 707-7833.
Biographical Note
Tony Schwartz, 1923-2008, was a media consultant, radio host and producer, educator, author, folk music documentarian and collector, and sound designer whose work has influenced many different aspects of the audiovisual landscape of the late 20th and early 21st centuries. He is most commonly associated with the “Daisy ad” he helped develop for Lyndon Baines Johnson’s 1964 presidential campaign against Barry Goldwater, a spot that aired only once but that nevertheless had a game-changing effect on political advertising. In the promotion of public health and civic issues, too, Schwartz applied innovative advertising and marketing techniques, most notably with a sustained series of campaigns against smoking and tobacco companies. So powerful was his first anti-smoking ad -- the first such ad ever produced -- that the tobacco industry voluntarily stopped advertising on radio and television.
Less widely known but hardly less significant than his work in advertising was Schwartz's inventive use of audio technology. Over the length of his career, Tony Schwartz pioneered many techniques and approaches to working with sound. He embraced recording technologies developed during World War II, not only adopting the reel-to-reel tape recorder as early as 1945, but also adapting it: he modified an early commercial tape recorder for portability by adding a shoulder strap and an internal power source. With the recorder slung over his shoulder, he ventured onto the streets of New York to record what he heard, from the sounds of nature to the unpredictable and rich variety of sounds produced by people.
Born August 19, 1923, Tony Schwartz was educated at Peekskill High School and the Pratt Institute. After a stint in the Navy during World War II, he began his advertising career as an art director. Schwartz's spur-of-the-moment purchase of a Webster wire recorder soon pointed him in a new direction, however. Deeply interested in folk music, he recorded radio programs such as Oscar Brand’s Folksong Festival and invited performers like Pete Seeger, Harry Belafonte, Jean Ritchie, and Woody Guthrie to record in the studio he built in his home on W. 56th Street. His tape exchange program, in which Schwartz swapped music with folklorists and collectors around the world, resulted in a collection of well over 30,000 songs and tunes from 46 countries. The folk music recordings he made in his home studio, acquired from other enthusiasts, and discussed as a guest on a WNYC radio program attracted the attention of artist and Sears-Roebuck heir William Rosenwald, whose financial support led to Schwartz's next endeavor: recording the sounds and music of New York City, or rather, one part of that city.
Tony Schwartz lived with a pronounced agoraphobia that prevented him from traveling beyond a small section of Manhattan, specifically the area known for much of his life as Postal Zone 19. His ability to discover and capture the stories, songs, games, and everyday sounds of work and play in that lively New York neighborhood, combined with the sheer size and wealth of his folk music collection, led, nevertheless, to a productive relationship with both Folkways and Columbia Records. Schwartz’s first two releases on Folkways, 1, 2, 3 and a Zing Zing Zing (Folkways FW07003, 1953) and New York 19 (Folkways FW 05558, 1954), were followed by titles like Nueva York: A Documentary of Puerto Rican New Yorkers (Folkways FW 05559, 1955), An Actual Story in Sound of a Dog's Life (Folkways FW05580, 1958), and The New York Taxi Driver (Columbia ML5309, 1959). The sounds of his neighborhood, as well as audio experiments he created (such as Jimmy Giuffre's clarinet playing juxtaposed against high heel clicks on a marble-floored lobby), were incorporated into his series of brief radio programs for WNYC and WBAI, Adventures in Sound (also known as Around New York) and Communications Journal. The series ran from the 1950s until 1976.
Schwartz's Folkways records received widespread attention, and he reentered advertising with a focus on sound as the primary means of communicating with an audience. He produced effective radio and television commercials for national brands such as Coca Cola, AT&T, Betty Crocker, and many more. Following the success and controversy of the “Daisy” political ad, Schwartz recorded thousands of spots for local, state, and national candidates, including Lyndon Johnson, Jimmy Carter, Edward Kennedy, Hubert Humphrey, Tom Foley, and Daniel Moynihan. Warren Rudman, a former Republican senator from New Hampshire, noted that "Tony Schwartz, as much as any person, laid the foundation for modern political advertising."
Later in his career, Schwartz consulted for various interest groups and organizations. He used the skills he developed in commercial and political advertising to focus attention on issues of public health and safety that were of personal interest to him, such as gun control, environmental protection, and combating tobacco use. Schwartz created anti-smoking campaigns for clients such as the American Cancer Society, Citizens for a Tobacco-Free Society, and the Non-smoker’s Rights Association. He also took on issues in his neighborhood and city, vigorously defending John Jay College for Criminal Justice from closure and supporting the New York City Patrolmen’s Benevolent Association (PBA).
Schwartz also worked as an educator. He shared the Schweizer Chair at Fordham University with Marshall McLuhan and taught courses in media theory for the Harvard University School of Public Health and Social Behavior, Emerson College, New York University’s Tisch School of the Arts, and the John Jay College of Criminal Justice. Focusing on his theories about communication and the use of audiovisual media in social and political discourse, Schwartz taught from his home office, communicating with his students via the telephone and incorporating sound and visual elements to illustrate his lectures.
Tony Schwartz made little distinction between his professional and personal activities; he worked almost exclusively from his home for much of his career and the voices of his wife, Reenah, and his children, Kayla and Anton, may be heard on many his recordings. Schwartz's business activities grew and developed from interests that he explored first as hobbies, such as recording sound and collecting folk music. His curiosity about communication through electronic media introduced him to Marshall McLuhan and resulted in his reputation as a published media theorist. His innovative advertising work led to influential political consulting, and he later used these skills to support causes and social issues that mattered to him personally. As a result, the rich collection of material he left behind defies easy classification.
Scope and Content Note
The Tony Schwartz Collection consists of multiple formats of material containing the products of his work as a media consultant, audio documentarian, author, radio producer, media theorist, and educator, as well as the research, consultation, preparation and editing, testing, and revision that led to his published textual and media-based works. Also included are published writings and videos about Schwartz, correspondence with colleagues and clients, and extensive files about people, organizations, and topics that interested Schwartz during his long and productive career.
The Biographical and Personal Materials series contains folders of material on Schwartz's early life, although these materials are not extensive. There are also photographs, biographical materials, and artifacts relating to colleagues and members of his family; publications and documentation relating to his health; family and other personal correspondence; awards and honorary degrees; publications and publicity materials concerned with Schwartz; and extensive documentation on the collection itself created by Schwartz and various interns and employees. Extremely useful, these collection lists, catalogs, and databases describe much but not all of the collection.
Series 2, Business and Professional Materials, forms the core of the Tony Schwartz Collection. There are boxes of general business materials such as address and appointment books; contact and client lists; business correspondence; documents relating to his company, New Sounds, Inc.; and some of the actual equipment he used, such as a timer, a teleprompter, and two patch bays with VU meters. His collaborations with other media consultants and advertising experts, notably Joseph Napolitan, are included as well.
Scripts, photographs, correspondence, and research materials that document work for specific people and organizations are divided into three client groups: political, public service, and commercial. Political candidates who hired Schwartz to work on their campaigns (at the local, state, and national levels) included Phil Bredesen, Jimmy Carter, Bill Clinton, Michael Dukakis, Tom Foley, Mike Gravel, Hubert Humphrey, Lyndon Johnson, Robert and Edward Kennedy, George McGovern, Ed Mezvinsky, Walter Mondale, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Claiborne Pell, Harry Reid, Abraham Ribicoff, Jay Rockefeller, Warren Rudman, Alex Seith, Isaac Newton Skelton, Ed Vrdolyak, Andrew Young, and many more.
Schwartz produced public service announcements for a wide variety of organizations, anti-smoking groups in particular (for example, the American Cancer Society, Patrick Reynolds Foundation for a Smokefree America, the American Lung Association, the American Heart Association, People for a Smoke-Free Indoors, and Doctors Ought to Care). Other issues represented in his public service work were AIDS awareness (AIDS Medical Foundation, Families Concerned about AIDS), public health (Minnesota Moms for Healthy Babies, New York City Department of Health), education (John Jay College of Criminal Justice, Action Committee for Higher Education), crime prevention (Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, Crimestoppers), fire safety (New York City Fire Department), handgun control (Handgun Control, Inc., Center to Prevent Handgun Violence), the environment (Florence and John Schumann Foundation, Forum for Environmental Stewardship), organized labor (Fraternal Order of Police, Lodge 5, International Association of Firefighters, Local 22 ), civil rights (NAACP, Anti-Defamation League of the B'nai B'rith), and local concerns (Coalition to Save Naumburg Bandshell, Arson on W. 56th Street).
Commercial/for-profit clients and products for which Schwartz produced ads included Apple computers, Excedrin, Bamberger's Department Store, Fortunoff Department Stores, General Electric, Hoffman-LaRoche, Inc., Kavanagh's Furniture Store, various radio and television networks and stations, Merck, Mobil Corporation, Pepsi-Cola, St. Lukes/Roosevelt Medical Center, Upjohn Rogaine, and Zenith.
The remainder of the Business and Professional series is concerned with Schwartz's broadcasting and recorded work (such as a press release and program guide relating to his long-running WNYC radio program); program proposals and courses he taught at Harvard University School of Public Health, Fordham University, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, New York University, Tisch School of the Arts, and elsewhere; speaking and media appearances (such as his appearances on the David Frost and Phil Donahue TV shows, and his talks at New York bistro Chez Beauvais); and various exhibitions.
Works and publications by Tony Schwartz are the focus of series 3. Included are production materials, scripts, correspondence, publicity materials, and reviews of published sound recordings such as his Folkways and Columbia Records releases (New York 19, Nueva York, Children at Play, and more). There are also materials documenting the development and release of Schwartz video recordings produced by David Hoffman and his company, Varied Directions, including Guerrilla Media, If You Know Someone Who Smokes, and Secrets of Effective Radio Advertising.
Materials on Schwartz’s published books, The Responsive Chord (1973) and Media, the Second God (1981, 1983), his many Media Industry Newsletter columns (1967-2004), and various other published articles and unpublished drafts and outlines may be found in the Writings grouping in series 3.
Series 4 consists of files on people, organizations, and topics of interest to Schwartz. Two subjects are documented extensively: Schwartz's transcribed interviews with Marshall McLuhan and published materials about smoking.
Several thousand sound recordings and hundreds of films and videocassettes, most of them relating to topics documented in the paper and graphic materials, are being digitally preserved by the Library of Congress for future public access. These audio and moving image materials will form series 5 and 6 in the collection and will be described in more detail in an upcoming version of this finding aid. For details on recordings that are available for research purposes, contact the Recorded Sound Reference Center, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, Library of Congress, Washington, DC, 20540-4690; (202) 707-7833.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 4 series:
Series 1: Biographical and Personal Materials, 1931-2008
Series 2: Business and Professional Materials, 1940-2005
Series 3: Works and Publications, 1950-2004
Series 4: Subject Files, 1912-2005
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012618550
Container List
- Series 1. Biographical and Personal Materials, 1931–2008, 10.2 linear feet
  Biographical information about Tony Schwartz and his family, including correspondence, awards, and publications about Schwartz.
  - Biographical information, 1931-02–2003-11
    Documents from Schwartz's childhood and military service, such as school reports, government documents, student assignments, and medical documents, and a variety of material related to his family.
    - Material from Tony Schwartz's early life, 1931-02-24–1972-11-30 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Arranged chronologically.
    - Material related to military service, personal life, and early career, 1943–1972 (Box-folder 1/2)
      Includes Schwartz's first marriage certificate, war ration cards, selective service documents, and personal financial documents.
      - Peekskill High School yearbook, 1976–1980-02-08 (Box-folder 1/3)
        1976 edition of "The Searchlight," the Peekskill High School yearbook for the class of 1941; includes signed note from Marye A. Camp (Gallucci).
    - Material relating to Tony Schwartz's family, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Material from or about Tony Schwartz's family, undated (Box-folder 1/4)
        Photocopies of a recipe for chocolate cake attributed to Esther Schwartz, Tony Schwartz's mother, and an obituary for John Zarach Levy.
      - "REENAH" clock, undated (Box 213)
        Handmade rectangular 11x14x1 1/4 inch clock illustrated with a black-and-white photographic image of Charlie Chaplin; the letters "R E E N A H" replace numbers on the clock face.
        "REENAH" refers to Reenah Schwartz, Tony Schwartz's wife.
      - Material about Michaela (Kayla) Schwartz, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
        Resume for Tony Schwartz's daughter, Kayla Schwartz; an article on her "Hand Holding and More" business; Smith College commencement announcement; and other material.
      - Material about Anton Schwartz, 1980–1998 (Box-folder 1/6)
        Includes low-resolution photographs of Tony Schwartz's son, Anton Schwartz, and a young woman. Originals may be printed by thermal printer; enlarged photocopies included. Advertisement/biography of Anton Schwartz in Intercom newsletter. Three photocopies of a one-page biography of Anton; color printout of photo; black and white photo of Anton turned into a Father's Day card.
      - Material about Connie Lukeian, 1989-02-07 (Box-folder 1/7)
        Brief biography and obituary for Connie Lukeian, Reenah Schwartz's sister. Also includes three copies of programs from a memorial held at the San Jose Unified School District; remarks from a memorial; an article from the San Jose Mercury News; and a copy of On Stage magazine from 1989-01.
        Photocopies.
      - Color photographs of Tony Schwartz family members and friends, circa 1980s–1990s (Box 201)
        Thirty-three miscellaneous color photographs of Tony Schwartz, his wife Reenah Schwartz, and his daughter Kayla and son Anton Schwartz, with various friends and possibly relatives. Also included are color snapshots of two [family?] dogs and a series of images that appear to have been reproduced through a color [inkjet?] printer. Two prints show Schwartz with an unidentified man [at the FBI Academy in Quantico, Virginia?]. Some of the photographic prints match color negatives of Schwartz family members and friends in box 204, folders 1-3.
      - Color negatives of Tony Schwartz family members and friends, circa 1980s–1990s (Box-folder 204/1-3)
        Eighteen strips of 35 mm color negative images of Tony Schwartz, his wife Reenah Schwartz, and his daughter Kayla and son Anton Schwartz, with various friends and possibly relatives. One negative strip shows Schwartz with an unidentified man [at the FBI Academy in Quantico, Virginia?], and there are also shots of Schwartz and others in his home recording studio, an anti-smoking poster, and family members packing up a car. Some of the negative images match color photographic prints of Schwartz family members and friends in box 201.
      - Color photographs of Tony Schwartz with family members, [1980s?] (Box-folder 225/1)
        Two color photographic prints (possibly printed on a color [inkjet?] printer); several copies of each. One image shows Tony and wife Reenah Schwartz looking at a black-and-white image of son Anton Schwartz displayed on a monitor or television screen. The other shows Tony Schwartz on the telephone. Both appear to have been taken in Schwartz's home studio.
    - Health-related documents